A Guide to the The Papers of William Francis Rhea 1899-1902
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Papers of William Francis Rhea 1899-1902
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12094
These papers consist of ca. 316 items, (1 Hollinger box, .5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Stuart Lutz, Historical Documents, Jersey City, New Jersey, October 23, 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Francis Rhea was born on a farm near Bristol, Virginia, on April 20, 1858, and attended rural and private schools. In 1878, he graduated from King College, Bristol, Tennessee, began to study law, and was admitted to the Virginia bar in 1879. Rhea served as a judge in both the Washington County Court and Bristol, Virginia, city court. He was first elected as a Democrat to the Virginia State Senate, 1885-1888, and then served two terms in the United States Congress, 1899-1903. After his defeat in the 1902 election, he again practiced law in Bristol, until his appointment as a member of the State corporation commission, 1908-1925, when he lived in Richmond, Virginia, until his death in 1931.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the political papers of Virginia Representative and judge of the Washington County Court (1880-1885) and the city court of Bristol, Virginia, William Francis Rhea (1858-1931), 1899- 1902, ca. 316 items (1 Hollinger box), chiefly constituent mail and papers pertaining to the election dispute between Rhea and James Alexander Walker (1832-1901) in the 1898 Congressional election for the Ninth District of Virginia.
Papers concerning the contested election are grouped together and include correspondence of the Campaign Committee with attorneys involved in the contest about their fees; other material about expenditures and fees connected to the disputed election; letters from registrars to Rhea regarding his request for lists of registered voters; miscellaneous documents and notes; lists of voting registrars in the 9th Congressional District; and Voting Rolls for Pulaski County and Russell County, Virginia, listing the registrar's name and address, and the voter's name, address, occupation and politics. According to the letters from the registrars to Rhea, most of them did not include the names of African-American voters on the voting rolls sent to Judge Rhea. Many of these African-American voters were expected to have cast Republican votes for Walker.
Constituent mail is concerned with applications for patronage positions, especially with the Census Bureau and Post Office; requests from farmers for the free blackleg vaccine, flower bulbs, seeds, literature printed by the government, and school superintendent positions. There were also letters opposing the Loud Bill concerning second-class mailing fees.
Other papers include financial documents of the Democratic Campaign Committee; an official ballot from the election held on November 6, 1900, with a letter from the Court Clerk Kilgore certifying its authenticity, January 8, 1902; Washington County receipts for [Claude] Swanson, 1901; a printed bill pertaining to copyright law and a report on "Measurements of Flow on the Holston River, Tennessee, June 10, 1902."
Contents List
- Constituent Mail - Applications for Promotions and Positions 1900
- Constituent Mail - Blackleg Vaccine 1900 Feb
- Constituent Mail - Census Applications 1899-1900
- Constituent Mail - Claims Against the Federal Government 1899-1901
- Constituent Mail - Flower Bulbs Distribution 1900
- Constituent Mail - Literature Distribution 1899-1901
- Constituent Mail - the Loud Bill 1900
- Constituent Mail - Post Office Applications, Questions, Complaints 1899-1900
- Constituent Mail - School Superintendent Applications 1900-1901
- Constituent Mail - Seed Distribution 1900-1901
- Election Dispute of Rhea and Walker - Correspondence of Campaign Committee and Attorneys involved in the contest case concerning fees 1900 Apr
- Election Dispute of Rhea and Walker - Expenditures and Fees 1899-1900
- Election Dispute of Rhea and Walker - Letters from Registrars regarding the request of Judge Rhea for lists of voters 1899-1900
- Election Dispute of Rhea and Walker - Miscellaneous Documents and Notes ca. 1899-1901
- Financial Papers of the Democratic Campaign Committee 1900-1901
- Lists of Voting Registrars in the 9th Congressional District 1899-1900
- Official Ballot from an election held on November 6, 1900, with a letter from Court Clerk W.E. Kilgore certifying its authenticity 1902 Jan 8
- Printed Bill relating to copyright and a Report "Measurements of Flow on the Holston River, Tennessee, made for James Gannon, Bristol, Tennessee" 1901-1902
- Voting Rolls - Pulaski County [1899-1900]
- Voting Rolls - Russell County [1899-1900]
- Washington County Receipts for [Claude] Swanson 1901